<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Cody Schroeder</origin>
        <origin>Hall Sawyer</origin>
        <pubdate>20201109</pubdate>
        <title>Migration stopovers of mule deer in the Sheep Creek Range, Nevada</title>
        <edition>Version 1.0</edition>
        <geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9O2YM6I</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Matthew Kauffman</origin>
            <origin>Holly Copeland</origin>
            <origin>Jodi Berg</origin>
            <origin>Scott Bergen</origin>
            <origin>Eric K. Cole</origin>
            <origin>Matthew Cuzzocreo</origin>
            <origin>Sarah Dewey</origin>
            <origin>Julien Fattebert</origin>
            <origin>Jeff Gagnon</origin>
            <origin>Emily Gelzer</origin>
            <origin>Chris Geremia</origin>
            <origin>Tabitha Graves</origin>
            <origin>Kent Hersey</origin>
            <origin>Mark Hurley</origin>
            <origin>Rusty Kaiser</origin>
            <origin>James Meacham</origin>
            <origin>Jerod Merkle</origin>
            <origin>Arthur Middleton</origin>
            <origin>Tristan Nunez</origin>
            <origin>Brendan Oates</origin>
            <origin>Daniel Olson</origin>
            <origin>Lucas Olson</origin>
            <origin>Hall Sawyer</origin>
            <origin>Cody Schroeder</origin>
            <origin>Scott Sprague</origin>
            <origin>Alethea Steingisser</origin>
            <origin>Mark Thonhoff</origin>
            <pubdate>20201001</pubdate>
            <title>Ungulate Migrations of the Western United States</title>
            <geoform>publication</geoform>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3133/sir20205101</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Mule deer in the Sheep Creek sub herd are part of the larger Area 6 herd that occupies portions of Elko, Lander, and Eureka counties. The primary winter range of this population is located along the eastern flank of the Sheep Creek Range and the west side of Boulder Valley. Most deer migrate approximately 30 miles from winter ranges in upper Boulder Creek and Antelope Creek drainages to summer ranges on the west side of the Tuscarora Mountains. However, some deer in this population migrate much farther – approximately 80 miles – and connect with mule deer that summer east of the Humboldt River. This deer herd faces several challenges, including migration routes that pass through increased mineral extraction activities in the Carlin Mine area, invasion of exotic annual grasses on winter range, increased wildfires on winter range, and deteriorated range conditions on many stopover sites and winter range due to overgrazing by livestock.

These data provide the location of migration stopovers for mule deer (Odocoileus hemionus) in the Sheep Creek Range, Nevada. They were developed from Brownian bridge movement models (Sawyer et al. 2009) using  68 migration sequences collected from a sample size of  36 animals comprising GPS locations collected every 1-25 hours.</abstract>
      <purpose>Across the western United States, many ungulate herds must migrate seasonally to access resources and avoid harsh winter conditions. Because these corridors traverse vast landscapes (i.e., up to 150 miles), they are increasingly threatened by roads, fencing, subdivisions and other development. Over the last decade, many new tracking studies have been conducted on migratory herds, and analytical methods have been developed that allow for population-level corridors and stopovers to be mapped and prioritized. In 2018, the U.S. Geological Survey assembled a Corridor Mapping Team to provide technical assistance to western states working to map bison, elk, moose, mule deer, and pronghorn corridors using existing GPS data. Based out of the Wyoming Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit, the team consists of federal scientists, university researchers, and biologists and analysts from participating state agencies. In its first year, the team has worked to develop a standardized analytical and computational methods and a workflow applicable to data sets typically collected by state agencies. In 2019, the team completed analyses necessary to map corridors, stopovers, and winter ranges in Arizona, Idaho, Nevada, Utah, and Wyoming. A total of 26 corridors, 16 migration routes, 25 stopovers, and 9 winter ranges, were mapped across these states and are included in this project. The Ungulate Migrations of the Western United States report and associated map archive provides the means for corridors to be taken into account by state and federal transportation officials, land and wildlife managers, planners, and other conservationists working to maintain big game corridors in the western states.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20110101</begdate>
          <enddate>20171201</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>observed</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-117.0517</westbc>
        <eastbc>-115.4004</eastbc>
        <northbc>41.6937</northbc>
        <southbc>40.7034</southbc>
      </bounding>
      <descgeog>Battle Mountain</descgeog>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
        <themekey>biota</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>migration (organisms)</themekey>
        <themekey>migratory species</themekey>
        <themekey>animal behavior</themekey>
        <themekey>stopovers</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:5f8db57182ce32418791d540</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Common geographic areas</placekt>
        <placekey>Carlin</placekey>
        <placekey>Nevada</placekey>
        <placekey>USA</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
    <useconst>Users are required to properly attribute this dataset.  Users are advised to read the dataset's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Cody Schroeder</cntper>
          <cntorg>Nevada Department of Wildlife</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Mule Deer Staff Specialist</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>6980 Sierra Center Pkwy Suite 120</address>
          <city>Reno</city>
          <state>Nevada</state>
          <postal>89509</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>775-688-1659</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>cschroeder@ndow.org</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>Nevada Department of Wildlife, Wildlife Heritage Trust Account, University of Nevada Reno</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Hall Sawyer</origin>
        <origin>Matthew J. Kauffman</origin>
        <origin>Ryan M. Nielson</origin>
        <origin>Jon S. Horne</origin>
        <pubdate>200912</pubdate>
        <title>Identifying and prioritizing ungulate migration routes for landscape-level conservation</title>
        <geoform>publication</geoform>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Ecological Applications</sername>
          <issue>vol. 19, issue 8</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>n/a</pubplace>
          <publish>Wiley</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <othercit>ppg. 2016-2025</othercit>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.1890/08-2034.1</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <taxonomy>
      <keywtax>
        <taxonkt>None</taxonkt>
        <taxonkey>Odocoileus hemionus</taxonkey>
      </keywtax>
      <taxoncl>
        <taxonrn>Kingdom</taxonrn>
        <taxonrv>Animalia</taxonrv>
        <taxoncl>
          <taxonrn>Subkingdom</taxonrn>
          <taxonrv>Bilateria</taxonrv>
          <taxoncl>
            <taxonrn>Infrakingdom</taxonrn>
            <taxonrv>Deuterostomia</taxonrv>
            <taxoncl>
              <taxonrn>Phylum</taxonrn>
              <taxonrv>Chordata</taxonrv>
              <taxoncl>
                <taxonrn>Subphylum</taxonrn>
                <taxonrv>Vertebrata</taxonrv>
                <taxoncl>
                  <taxonrn>Infraphylum</taxonrn>
                  <taxonrv>Gnathostomata</taxonrv>
                  <taxoncl>
                    <taxonrn>Superclass</taxonrn>
                    <taxonrv>Tetrapoda</taxonrv>
                    <taxoncl>
                      <taxonrn>Class</taxonrn>
                      <taxonrv>Mammalia</taxonrv>
                      <taxoncl>
                        <taxonrn>Subclass</taxonrn>
                        <taxonrv>Theria</taxonrv>
                        <taxoncl>
                          <taxonrn>Infraclass</taxonrn>
                          <taxonrv>Eutheria</taxonrv>
                          <taxoncl>
                            <taxonrn>Order</taxonrn>
                            <taxonrv>Artiodactyla</taxonrv>
                            <taxoncl>
                              <taxonrn>Family</taxonrn>
                              <taxonrv>Cervidae</taxonrv>
                              <taxoncl>
                                <taxonrn>Subfamily</taxonrn>
                                <taxonrv>Capreolinae</taxonrv>
                                <taxoncl>
                                  <taxonrn>Genus</taxonrn>
                                  <taxonrv>Odocoileus</taxonrv>
                                  <common>mule deer</common>
                                  <taxoncl>
                                    <taxonrn>Species</taxonrn>
                                    <taxonrv>Odocoileus hemionus</taxonrv>
                                    <common>TSN: 180698</common>
                                  </taxoncl>
                                </taxoncl>
                              </taxoncl>
                            </taxoncl>
                          </taxoncl>
                        </taxoncl>
                      </taxoncl>
                    </taxoncl>
                  </taxoncl>
                </taxoncl>
              </taxoncl>
            </taxoncl>
          </taxoncl>
        </taxoncl>
      </taxoncl>
    </taxonomy>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>We checked to ensure values were in expected ranges (e.g. locations of corridors were as expected, and dates of GPS observations were consistent with the project time period), completeness, and there were no errors of omission.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>We checked to ensure values were in expected ranges and locations (e.g. locations of corridors were as expected, and dates of GPS observations were consistent with the project time period).</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>We checked to ensure there were no locations outside of the expected regions.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>We checked to ensure there were no locations outside of the expected regions.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>We applied a three-step process to calculate population-level corridors and to identify stopovers, which generally followed the approach outlined by Sawyer et al. (2009). First, we averaged the utilization distribution (UD) for a given individual’s spring and fall migration sequences across all years to produce a single, individual-level migration UD. We rescaled this averaged UD to sum to one. We then defined a migration footprint for each individual as the 99% isopleth of this UD. We stacked up all the individual footprints for a given population, and defined different levels of corridor use based on the number of individuals using a given pixel. We defined low-use corridors as areas traversed by ≥1 individual during migration, medium-use corridors were used by ≥10% of individuals within the population, and high-use corridors were used by ≥20% individuals within the population. We then converted these corridors from a raster format to a polygon/vector format. Furthermore, we removed polygons of less than 20,000 m2 (i.e., less than approximately 5 acres), which can represent spatially isolated use by just a single animal and do not meet the definition of a corridor.</procdesc>
        <procdate>20200518</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Vector</direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Albers Conical Equal Area</mapprojn>
          <albers>
            <stdparll>29.5</stdparll>
            <stdparll>45.5</stdparll>
            <longcm>-96.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>23.0</latprjo>
            <feast>0.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </albers>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.6096</absres>
            <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>North_American_Datum_1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS_1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>NV_MD_Area6_SheepCreek_Stopovers_Ver1_2019.shp Attribute Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer Defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>layer</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Stopover present</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer Defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1.0</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1.0</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>"The Nevada Department of Wildlife will retain ownership of the data provided and must approve of any additional use before other analyses, research, or publications are initiated. The burden for determining fitness for use lies entirely with the user. For purposes of publication or dissemination, citations, or credit should be given to the Nevada Department of Wildlife."</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>Digital Data</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <onlinopt>
            <computer>
              <networka>
                <networkr>https://doi.org/10.5066/P9O2YM6I</networkr>
              </networka>
            </computer>
          </onlinopt>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>none</fees>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20201109</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>US Geological Survey, Wyoming Cooperative Fish and Wildlife Research Unit, University of Wyoming</cntorg>
          <cntper>Matthew Kauffman</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>1000 E University Ave, Dept 3166</address>
          <city>Laramie</city>
          <state>WY</state>
          <postal>82071</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>307-766-6404</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Biological Data Profile of the Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001.1-1999</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
